<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document title="uPortal 1.0 Overview">
  <section title="Features">
    <itemgroup title="Personalization">
      <item>Choose color scheme</item>
      <item>Choose channels</item>
      <item>Arrange channels in a tab/column layout</item>
    </itemgroup>
    <itemgroup title="Publish">
      <item>Make a channel available for subscription</item>
    </itemgroup>
    <itemgroup title="Subscribe">
      <item>Browse and choose channels which are grouped by category</item>
      <item>Preview a channel before subscribing</item>
    </itemgroup>
    <itemgroup title="Included channels">
      <item>CApplet: Displays a java applet</item>
      <item>CAuthorization: Lets users log on</item>
      <item>CBookmarks: Lets users store their favorite web sites</item>
      <item>CInlineFrame: Displays an html page</item>
      <item>CPageRenderer: Displays an html page</item>
      <item>CRSSChannel: Displays an RSS channel</item>
      <item>CSearch: Provides a form for searching the web</item>
    </itemgroup>
  </section>
  
  <section title="Requirements">
    <item>A Java Servlet Engine/Container which is Servlet 2.2/JSP 1.1 compliant.
      uPortal has been tested under
      <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat">Tomcat</a>
      and Caucho's <a href="http://www.caucho.com/">Resin</a></item>
    <item>JDK 1.2.2 or higher Java Virtual Machine.
      uPortal has been tested on the SUN Virtual Machine,
      but not the Microsoft VM.</item>
    <item>Netscape Navigator 4.x or Internet Explorer 4.x as a minimum.
      Mozilla or Internet Explorer 5.x should also work fine.</item>
    <item>The ObjectSpace <a href="http://www.objectspace.com/products/prodDXML.asp">DXML</a> classes. 
      uPortal requires these classes to process XML.</item>
    <item>IBM's XML Parser For Java. DXML requires these classes for XML 
      parsing. The correct version of XML4J can be downloaded from ObjectSpace <a href="http://www.objectspace.com/downloads/xml4j.asp">here</a>.</item>
    <item>A JDBC compliant database. uPortal is developed using 
      <a href="http://hsql.oron.ch/">HypersonicSQL</a>. 
      Oracle has also been used. Any JDBC compliant database should work with 
      some modification to the CREATE scripts and some SQL statements.</item>     
    <item>An XSLT engine. uPortal used Apache's <a href="http://xml.apache.org/xalan/">Xalan.</a></item>
  </section>
  
  <section title="Installation">
    <item>uPortal is 100% Java and should therefore run on any platform.</item>
    <item>Move the "webpages" directory to "/webpages" under your web server.
      If you already have a "webpages" directory simply add the files there.</item>
    <item>Put all required class packages along with the uPortal classes 
      in the classpath of the servlet engine.</item>
    <item>Run Hypersonic (hsql) in client/server mode by initiating the RunWebServer script.
      After starting hsql, run the DatabaseManager applet and log into hsql as client/server using
      the default login. Load the scripts from the 'scripts' directory. Execute the scripts to
      create and populate the tables.</item>
	  <item>Set the portal base directory in the web.xml file.  Here is an example:
	    <pre>      &lt;web-app&gt;
        &lt;context-param&gt;
          &lt;param-name&gt;portalBaseDir&lt;/param-name&gt;
          &lt;param-value&gt;D:\Projects\JA-SIG\portal\&lt;/param-value&gt;
        &lt;/context-param&gt;
      &lt;/web-app&gt;</pre></item>
    <item>Start the servlet engine and load index.jsp in a web browser.</item>
  </section>
  
  <section title="CVS Access">
    <itemgroup title="All Users">
      <item>All users wishing to contribute to the project must first register with 
        the <a href="https://spackler.mis.udel.edu/ClearingHouse/index.jsp">JA-SIG 
        Clearinghouse</a>.
        The login and password you set here will be the login and password you 
        will use for accessing CVS.</item>
      <item>We have created a generic account on our server for logging in and creating 
        the SSH tunnel. The instructions for logging into this account will be sent you 
        upon <a href="mailto:John%20Laker%3Cjlaker@udel.edu%3E?subject=CVS%20Access%20Request">request</a>.</item>
    </itemgroup>
    <itemgroup title="CVS Access on Windows">
      <item>On Windows, you need to use a CVS client and SSH client/tunnel.
        <p>
            <ul>
                <li><a href="http://www.wincvs.org">WinCVS 1.1b7 or greater (GUI client)</a></li>
                <li><a href="http://www.mindbright.com/mindterm/">MindBright MindTerm 
                Java SSH</a></li>
            </ul></p></item>
        <p> You can find other SSH clients <a href="http://www.cs.hmc.edu/tech_docs/qref/ssh.html">here</a> 
            but the above are the only ones recommended since they do SSH tunneling 
            (most SSH clients just do terminal emulation).</p>
        <p> In addition, if you are behind a corporate firewall, your best option 
            is to use a socks proxy. Most SSH software knows how to traverse socks 
            proxies. In addition, there are socks utility programs that let you &quot;sockisfy&quot; 
            any application. Contact your sysadmin for details.</p>
        
      <item>How to Connect using MindTerm and WinCVS
        <p> This is an illustrated example showing the MindTerm program and the 
            WinCVS CVS GUI client. </p>
        <p> Assuming you have installed the Mindterm classes (or .jar archive) on 
            your system classpath (and, of course, that you have a Java virtual machine 
            available on your system), the first step is turn on the client. From 
            the DOS prompt type: </p>
        <blockquote> <code>java mindbright.application.MindTerm</code> </blockquote>
        <p> Now, go to the <em>tunnels</em> menu and set is up so that local port 
            2401 is directed to host "localhost" on the same (you don't need to understand 
            why) as showed in the picture below: </p>
        <img src="images/mindterm_tunnel.gif" width="587" height="475"/> 
        <p> When this is done, go ahead and connect to SSH host <em>mis105.mis.udel.edu</em> 
            by typing so at the <code>SSH-server:</code> prompt. Then your username 
            will be requested and the password. Don't worry about transmitting your 
            password since SSH is done exactly to allow you to transmit your password 
            without worrying about sniffing and other security holes of normal remote 
            shells. </p>
        <p> When mis105 welcomes you and its prompt appears, you can safely minimize 
            your mindterm window since, for plain WinCVS operation, you won't need 
            to type anything in the ssh terminal. The WinCVS client will send CVS 
            commands thru the SSH tunnel transparently. </p>
        <p> Then launch the WinCVS client. The first time, it will ask you the basic 
            configuration preferences that it needs. These are the CVS repository 
            location and authentication information. The screenshot below tells you 
            what you should enter. Note that you must replace the string username 
            in the repository location with your own username on mis105. </p>
        <img src="images/wincvs_config.gif" width="618" height="390"/> 
        <p> At this point you software is setup and first thing to do is to authenticate 
            yourself on the CVS repository. This is done by logging in the server 
            with the menu <code>Admin -> Login</code> and inserting your password. 
            This action authenticates you into the CVS server and saves your password 
            (in a crypted form) in the <code>.cvspass</code> file in the home directory 
            you specify. Note that you need to do this only once per CVS repository, 
            not everytime you connect to it, even if you disconnected from that server. 
        </p>
        <p> Now your WinCVS client is ready to perform operations on the remote 
            CVS repository. First action to take is to <code>checkout</code> the <b>portal</b> 
            module. To do this, first select the directory where you want the files 
            to be located. Note that the files will be automatically placed in the 
            <code><b>portal</b></code> subdirectory of the indicated directory. Then 
            select the menu item <code>Create -> Checkout module...</code>. After 
            this, place <code><b>portal</b></code> in the module name field and you're 
            ready to go. </p></item>
    </itemgroup>
    <itemgroup title="CVS Access on Unix">
      <item><p>On Unix, you need the following software products: </p>
        <ul>
            <li><a href="http://download.cyclic.com/pub/">CVS client (pick up latest 
            version)</a></li>
            <li><a href="ftp://ftp.cs.hut.fi/pub/ssh/">SSH client (pick up 1.x, not 
            2.x)</a> </li>
        </ul>
        <p>Depending on your platform you may be able to pick up precompiled versions 
            or have to compile them yourself. </p></item>
      <item>Notes
        <p>Since both CVS and SSH are based on open standards, there are lots of 
            CVS and SSH tools freely available on the net, both of command line and 
            GUI behavior. This means that any compliant implementations of those standards 
            should work as well. </p>
        <p>For some more software options as well as other tips and tricks, see 
            www.hyperreal.org/info/ssh </p>
        <p>In addition, if you are behind a corporate firewall, your best option 
            is to use a socks proxy. Most SSH software knows how to traverse socks 
            proxies. In addition, there are socks utility programs that let you "sockisfy" 
            any application. Contact your sysadmin for details. </p></item>
      <item>How to Connect
        <p>The first step is to set up the SSH tunnel to mis105. To do this, you 
            need to have your SSH client software redirect your local port 2401 to 
            the far side of the SSH connection. The command looks something like this: 
        </p>
        <p><code>ssh -L 2401:localhost:2401 mis105.mis.udel.edu </code></p>
        <p>The next step is to use the CVS pserver functionality to login. You'll 
            want to do this in a seperate terminal from the one that you logged into 
            mis105 with so that you check out the files to your local machine and 
            not to your account on mis105! This command looks like this: </p>
        <p><code>cvs -d :pserver:user@localhost:/home/cvs/jasig login </code></p>
        <p>Note that the CVS client thinks it is talking to a server running on 
            your local machine, but in fact is talking to the CVS pserver on mis105 
            thanks to the SSH tunnel. After you login, you can check out any of the 
            source trees. The command to checkout the JA-SIG Portal source is: </p>
        <p><code>cvs -d :pserver:user@localhost:/home/cvs/jasig checkout portal 
            </code></p>
        <p>Once you checkout a source tree, all CVS operations in that source tree 
            do not require the <code>-d :pserver:</code> argument. </p>
        <p><font size="-1">Some of these instructions were obtained from the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/cvsindex.html">Apache 
            Jakarta Project</a>.</font> </p></item>
    </itemgroup>
  </section>
  
  <section title="uPortal 2.0">
    <item></item>
  </section>
  
</document>
