<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>
<ChapterText>
	<!--Text for the Demonstration Narrative channel-->
	<page>
		<heading>The Meteor Demonstration Channel</heading>
		<paragraph>
The Meteor Project portal has two Meteor channels--one for students and one for financial aid professionals. The student channel would be used by a prospective student or student to access their financial aid information. The financial aid professional may acces the information from any authorized student. The current implement only shows a list of loans the student may have. This list is based on the Loan Locator service of the National Student Clearinghouse.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
This demonstration site does not access either actual student data or information from Meteor data providers. All access uses a test database.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
The following demonstration will take you step-by-step through a typical session.
		</paragraph>
	</page>
	<page>
		<subheading>Access by a Financial Aid Professional</subheading>
		<paragraph>
The Fin Aid Professional Channel should be displayed. If not, click on "Fin Aid Professional" in the navigation tree on the left hand side of the display. The financial aid professional's channel should display a signon window as shown in Figure 5.
		</paragraph>
		<image>Figure_5</image>
		<caption>Figure 5 - Signon Screen for Financial Aid Professionals</caption>
		<paragraph>
This screen has two options for signon in the pull-down box. NSC refers to signons authenticated by the National Student Clearinghouse. SFA refers to signons authenticated by the Department of Education's Office of Student Financial Assistance. [Although shared authentication was announced December 14, 2000, subsequently SFA has said shared authentication will not be approved by the Social Security Administration. Like the SFA reference will be removed in future releases].
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>The following User Names and Passwords or PINs are valid for the test database:
			<bullet>SMU-KRS  8080</bullet>
			<bullet>SMU-JET  1111</bullet>
			<bullet>GSG-SSS  2222</bullet>
			<bullet>GSG-PRH  3333</bullet>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph> 
Let's begin by signing on using the first User Name and PIN as shown in Figure 5. Then click on Send Request. The next display will request a student's Social Security Number.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
When you click on Send Request, a business message is sent from the uPortal computer--the access provider--to the NSC computer--the data provider with the User Name and Password. Remember all Meteor messages are encrypted so the User Name and Password will only be available to the NSC computer. The NSC computer compares the User Name and Password or PIN to it current security directory. If there is a match, NSC returns a message authenticating the user and authorizing access. If there is no comparison, NSC returns an error message. If the user is authenticated, Meteor software presents a display requesting a student Social Security Number. This is shown in Figure 6.
		</paragraph>
		<image>Figure_6</image>
		<caption>Figure 6 - Request for a Student's Social Security Number</caption>
		<paragraph>The valid Social Security Numbers in the test database are:
			<bullet>158482387  1978-07-01</bullet>
			<bullet>448377707  1980-09-03</bullet>
			<bullet>836734909  1982-01-16</bullet>
			<bullet>496378213  1960-08-11</bullet>
			<bullet>197845937  1983-01-01</bullet>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
To show George Likens list of loans, let's enter his Social Security Number--the first of the valid Social Security Number and birthdate combinations. And click on Send Request. This will return the loan list for George Likens as shown in Figure 7.
		</paragraph>
		<image>Figure_7</image>
		<caption>Figure 7 - Student Loan List</caption>
		<paragraph>This is the same list of loans that would be obtained by George Likens if he had used the Student Channel.			</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
If a Social Security Number were entered for which there were no loans, an error would be returned. At the present time the only the error code is shown. In the future the message will say that no loans were found for the student. The current error code is shown in Figure 8		</paragraph>
		<image>Figure_8</image>
		<caption>Figure 8 - No Loans Found for a Student</caption>
		<paragraph>
After viewing the loan list, the financial aid professional may click on Return and enter another student's Social Security Number.
		</paragraph>
	</page>
</ChapterText>
