<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rss PUBLIC "-//Netscape Communications//DTD RSS 0.91//EN">
<rss version="0.91">
   <channel>
      <title>StockCharts.com</title>
      <link>http://stockcharts.com/</link>
      <description>Free Stock Charts and Expert Market Commentary</description>
      <language>en</language>
      <image>
         <title>StockCharts.com</title>
         <url>http://stockcharts.com/images/sccrss.gif</url>
         <link>http://stockcharts.com/</link>
         <width>88</width>
         <height>31</height>
         <description>Free Stock Charts and Expert Market Commentary</description>
      </image>
      <item>
         <title>What We're Watching Today</title>
         <link>http://stockcharts.com</link>
         <description>After a solid opening, the Nasdaq Composite fell sharply and formed a bearish engulfing pattern, the second such pattern this week. The yield on the long bond dropped below 6.60% for the first time since 10-Jan. The Dow Transports eeked out a small gain today after falling 10.93% during the previous 11 sessions.
 </description>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>StockWatch: Dell, GE, Cisco  - Arthur Hill</title>
         <link>http://stockcharts.com/commentary/stockWatch/index.html</link>
         <description>The latest charts for  Dell, GE, and Cisco, from our chief analyst, Arthur Hill.</description>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Market Sentiment Charts - Jeff Walker</title>
         <link>http://stockcharts.com/charts/sentiment/index.html</link>
         <description>Every week the readers at LowRisk.com predict what the Dow Jones Industrial Average will do next. Jeff Walker compiles the sentiment data, and Stockcharts.com charts it. </description>
      </item>

      <item>
         <title>Mid-Life Growth Investment Strategies - Scott McCormick</title>
         <link>http://stockcharts.com/commentary/scottmc/scottmc20000125.html</link>
         <description>Tactical asset management, and the myth of timeliness -- how do these affect the investment strategies you should follow in mid-life? Scott says to pick a triggering event as a review reminder.</description>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Promising High-Tech Small Caps - Paulo Prazeres</title>
         <link>http://stockcharts.com/commentary/paulo/paulo20000124.html</link>
         <description>Everyone is talking about Small Caps, including Paulo. He examines three promising picks -- e.Digital, US Video and iVoice -- and revisits his Dow 12,000 prediction.</description>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Do Interest Rates Matter? - John Murphy</title>
         <link>http://stockcharts.com/commentary/murphy/Murphy20000122.html</link>
         <description>Historically, the direction of interest rates has had a major impact on stock prices.  Is that still true in this "new" economy? John looks at the past and sets a new target for bonds.</description>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Chart Watchers Weekly - Latest Issue</title>
         <link>http://stockcharts.com/commentary/archives/cww20000121.html</link>
         <description>In this issue: weekly market performance summary and analysis; strange divergences between the S&amp;P 500, and the S&amp;P 400 and S&amp;P 600; market breadth indicators are moving higher (!); new feature -- Bolllinger Band scans.</description>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>VIX &amp; the Russell 2000/CCI - Rex Takasugi</title>
         <link>http://stockcharts.com/commentary/rex/RexTak20000121.html</link>
         <description>There were lots of questions about the VIX chart in last week's column, so Rex explains how he uses this popular index. He also shows how the CCI has recently worked well with the Russell 2000. </description>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Education: Price Oscillator - Arthur Hill</title>
         <link>http://stockcharts.com/education/indic_priceOscillator.html</link>
         <description>This popular indicator allows comparisons across time periods, regardless of the price of the stock. As a bonus, we include information about PPO-Histogram, too! (Hint: it's a lot like MACD-Histogram.)</description>
      </item>
      <item>
         <title>Rock and Roll Bearishness - Walker Market Letter</title>
         <link>http://stockcharts.com/commentary/walker/walker20000118.html</link>
         <description>Jeff Walker thinks the market is putting in an intermediate-term top here -- that the next big move will be down.  </description>
      </item>
      <textinput>
         <title>P&amp;F Chart</title>
         <description>Enter any US stock, index, or mutual fund symbol:</description>
         <name>symbol</name>
         <link>http://www.stockcharts.com/cgi-bin/PnFForm.pl</link>
      </textinput>
   </channel>
</rss>
