<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>
<PageViewer>
	<ID>DemoStudent</ID>
	<ChapterText>
		<!--Text for the Demonstration Narrative channel-->
		<page>
			<heading>The Meteor Demonstration Channel</heading>
			<paragraph>
The Meteor Project portal has two Meteor channels--one for students and one for financial aid professionals. The student channel would be used by a prospective student or student to access their financial aid information. The financial aid professional may acces the information from any authorized student. The current implementation only shows a list of loans the student may have. This list is based on the Loan Locator service of the National Student Clearinghouse. The next implementation will include detail on each loan that has more data available.
		</paragraph>
			<paragraph>
This demonstration does not access either actual student data or information from Meteor data providers. All access is to a test database emulating the National Student Clearinghouse. An access server is running the uPortal that contains Meteor channels. The access server communicates, over the Internet, to a data provider server that, in turn, accesses a database server. The access server and data provider server are connected by the Internet. Business messages are exchanged between the two computers over the Internet.
		</paragraph>
			<paragraph>
The following demonstration will take you step-by-step through a typical query to find out what student loans a student may have.
		</paragraph>
		</page>
		<page>
			<subheading>Student Access</subheading>
			<paragraph>
The Student Channel should also be displayed. If not, click on "Student Financial Aid" in the navigation tree on the left hand side of the display. The Student Channel should display a signon window as shown in Figure 1.
		</paragraph>
			<image>
				<name>Figure_1</name>
				<relativeURL>meteor.jpg</relativeURL>
				<caption>Figure 1 - Student Signon Screen</caption>
			</image>
			<paragraph>
The following combinations of student Social Security Numbers and birthdates will retrieve loan information from the demonstration database. This version of the software does not edit the Social Security Number or date; they must be entered exactly as shown. In the future, the SSN may include hypens or blanks and several forms of the date may be used.
			<bullet>158482387  1978-07-01</bullet>
				<bullet>448377707  1980-09-03</bullet>
				<bullet>836734909  1982-01-16</bullet>
				<bullet>496378213  1960-08-11</bullet>
				<bullet>197845937  1983-01-01</bullet>
			</paragraph>
			<paragraph>If you entered the first Social Security Number and birthdate correctly and clicked on Send Request , you will see a display such as the one shown in Figure 2 for George Likens.
		</paragraph>
			<image>
				<name>Figure_2</name>
				<relativeURL>meteor.jpg</relativeURL>
				<caption>Figure 2 - Loan List for George Likens</caption>
			</image>
			<paragraph>
When you clicked on Send Request, an XML business message was composed by the access server using George's Social Security Number and date of birth. The format of that message followed the standards of the Department of Education's draft Common Record. That mesage was sent, over an encryption protected connection  using the SOAP protocol, to a server representing the National Student Clearinghouse. The Clearinghouse responded with an XML business message to the access server that runs the uPortal. The received business message was converted to the display you see using an XSL transformation (XSLT).
		</paragraph>
			<paragraph>
The other combinations of valid Social Security Numbers and birthdates will provide similar results.
		</paragraph>
		</page>
		<page>
			<paragraph>
Not all Social Security Numbers and birthdates will be entered correctly. Lets go back to George Liken's Social Security Number and birthdate. This time enter a birthdate of 1978-06-01--June instead of July. Then you get an error message like the one shown in Figure 3. The text "Birthdate does not match birthdate on loan records" came in the budinrdd message from the National Student Clearinghouse. When they compared th birthdate submitted by George to the birthdate on their records, it didn't match. In addition there is the note Error 1120. This refers to IFX standard message 1120. Error means the transaction could not be completed. Warning means a condition was found that may be an error, but the transaction was processed anyway. Info means some additional information should be provided, but the transaction appears to be processed correctly.
		</paragraph>
			<image>
				<name>Figure_3</name>
				<relativeURL>meteor.jpg</relativeURL>
				<caption>Figure 3 - Error Display for a Birthdate Error</caption>
			</image>
			<paragraph>
Let's go back and enter a Social Security Number that is not valid. Use 158482388 and George's birthdate of 1978-07-01 (actually any valid birthdate would have worked). Then you get the error display with the text "No loans found for this Social Security Number." The display, shown in Figure 4, also has Error 1120. The text means there were no loans for whoever has that Social Security Number. Since no records were found, the same error 1120, was displayed. 
		</paragraph>
			<image>
				<name>Figure_4</name>
				<relativeURL>meteor.jpg</relativeURL>
				<caption>Figure 4 - Error Display for a Social Security Number Error</caption>
			</image>
		</page>
	</ChapterText>
</PageViewer>
