<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

  <!--
  <!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd" >
  -->

  <!--
   Author:   Bill Brooks   wbrooks@lug.ee.calpoly.edu
   Filename: Authorization.xml
   Creation: 
   Revision: $Revision$ 
   Language: XML 1.0 (DocBook XML DTD v4.1.2)
   Purpose:  Documents compilation process for uPortal 2.x
   $Id$
   -->
   



<article status="draft">
  <articleinfo>
    <copyright>
      <year>2000</year>
      <year>2001</year>
      <holder>JA-SIG</holder>
    </copyright>
    
    <author>
      <firstname>Bill</firstname>
      <surname>Brooks</surname>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>California Polytechnic State University</orgname>
        <orgdiv>ITS Application and Information Management</orgdiv>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <author>
      <firstname>Ken</firstname>
      <surname>Weiner</surname>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Interactive Business Solutions</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <author>
      <firstname>Peter</firstname>
      <surname>Kharchecnko</surname>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Interactive Business Solutions</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

     <date>December 23, 2001</date>

     <title>uPortal 2.0 Overview
     </title>

  <!--
     <revhistory>
        <revision>
           <revnumber>0.1</revnumber>
           <date>December 23, 2001</date>
           <revremark>Baselined</revremark>
        </revision>
     </revhistory>
   -->
   
  </articleinfo>
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    
    <para>This document provides a concise overview of the steps you'll take to generate a portal
    instance with the JA-SIG <productname>uPortal</productname> framework. We'll assume you have 
    extensive, recent experience with server-side Java application development and have an intimate
    understanding of the operating system and configuration of the computer system on which 
    you are attempting to install the portal. 
    </para>

    <para>The first thing you must decide is how you're going to work with the 
    <productname>uPortal</productname> framework to produce a portal instance at your site. Releases of
    <productname>uPortal</productname> come in two forms: The <quote>quick start</quote> releases
    and the standalone source code. 
    </para>

    <sect2>
       <title>Choosing A Release of <productname>uPortal</productname></title>
       
       <para>Making the choice as to which of the two major kinds of <productname>uPortal</productname>
       releases is right for you involves examining what you're trying to immediately achieve. If you're
       just attempting to get started with <productname>uPortal</productname> in order to see what features
       it supports, what it requires in terms of personnel, hardware and software support or to assess how
       it compares to other portal vendor's products, then the <quote>Quick Start</quote> Releases are for
       you. If you're trying to get a portal instance configured and installed for production use on
       your campus, or if you're a developer who requires an instance of the portal so that you can develop
       content or applications for use with your campus' portal, then you'll probably work with the
       <productname>uPortal</productname> sources as they are released from the JA-SIG CVS repository. 
       Compiling <productname>uPortal</productname> from source is the best way to make sure you can get
       your instance working with your particular development and deployment environments.
       </para>
       
       <sect3 id="quickstart">
          <title>The <productname>uPortal</productname> <quote>Quick Start</quote> Releases</title>
          
          <para>The <quote>Quick Start</quote> releases are assembled so they can be downloaded
          and run with a minimum of effort, and they include all the software necessary to run an 
          instance of the portal except an operating system, JVM and web browser. Assuming that you
          already have these three items installed, you can start using the portal instance provided
          with a <quote>Quick Start</quote> release just a few minutes after you complete the download 
          processs. 
          </para>
          
          <para><orgname>JA-SIG</orgname> produces the <quote>Quick Start</quote> releases to make it easy 
          for campuses to evaluate the <productname>uPortal</productname> framework and decide if it meets 
          their needs. <orgname>JA-SIG</orgname>  realizes that some university IT departments operate in a
          <quote>demo-driven</quote> management decision-making environment and that IT staff who are 
          attempting to make a rational choice among portal vendors often have to compete with slick sales
          presentations from marketing and sales staff from major software vendors. The <quote>Quick Start
          </quote> releases enable those IT staff members to get a demo of a <productname>uPortal</productname>
          -based portal going quickly so that managers can get a better idea of how 
          <productname>uPortal</productname> stacks up against products from those vendors. 
          </para>
          
          <para>The <quote>Quick Start</quote> releases aren't appropriate if your intent is to produce a
          production portal instance for deployment on your campus. For production use, you're highly
          likely to want to customize the look and feel of the portal to reflect the published style guide
          for websites at your institution. You're also likely to already have a web application
          infrastructure (meaning a web server, Java servlet/JSP container, relational database management 
          system, directory server, ERPs, etc.) that you want your portal to utilize so that you leverage 
          existing information systems. Although you could use the <quote>Quick Start</quote> releases as a
          starting point and customize the portal instance that ships until it meets your needs, ultimately you
          will spend more time than if you started with the standalone sources from the source code repository.
          (see <xref linkend="cvssources" />, below). 
          </para>
          
          
       </sect3>
       
       <sect3 id="cvssources">
          <title>The <productname>uPortal</productname> Source Code</title>
          
          <para>As an open source project, <orgname>JA-SIG</orgname> makes the full source code for the
          <productname>uPortal</productname> framework available to member institutions at no cost. While
          working with the standalone <productname>uPortal</productname> sources directly involves more 
          up-front compilation and configuration work to produce a working portal instance, it provides you
          with the maximum amount of flexibility in producing what you deploy, either in production for use
          by end-users on your campus or in development for use by your content producers or application 
          programmers.
         </para>
         
         <para>
         Working with the <productname>uPortal</productname> sources isn't the best method of producing
         a portal instance if you just want to get an instance of a portal up and running quickly to 
         <quote>kick the tires</quote>, see what it looks like or see what features it supports. If you're just
         attempting to evaluate <productname>uPortal</productname>, you can do so in less time than compiling the
         <productname>uPortal</productname> sources requires by downloading and installing the latest 
         <quote>Quick Start</quote> release(skip the next section and see <xref linkend="quickstart" />, below). 
         </para>
       </sect3>
       
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="prerequisites" >
       <title>Prerequisites for compiling and installing <productname>uPortal</productname>
        From Source</title>
        
        <para>In order to compile the <productname>uPortal</productname> framework from source to
         produce an installation of a portal at your site, you must first have some tools 
         installed on the computer you plan to use to run the portal on. Before proceeding with the
         following instructions, obtain and install the following:
         
         <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
            <listitem>
              <para>A CVS client for your operating system. 
              </para>
            </listitem>         
            <listitem>
              <para>A JDK 1.2.2 or higher Java Virtual Machine. <productname>uPortal</productname> has
              been tested extensively using the Sun and IBM Virtual Machines.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>A copy of Ant. Ant is a build tool for Java developed by the 
              <ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant">Apache Jakarta Project</ulink>. 
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>A Java Servlet Container which is complaint with the Servlets 2.2 specification.
              <productname>uPortal</productname> has been tested extensively using the Apache Jakarta Project's 
              <ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat">Tomcat</ulink> Servlet
              Container and web server, but any Servlets 2.2 compliant container should work. 
              </para>
            </listitem>       
            <listitem>
              <para>A fourth generation web browser. Netscape Navigator 4.x or Internet Explorer 4.x
              as a minimum. Mozilla or Internet Explorer 5.x should also work fine.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>A relational database management system (RDBMS) with a JDBC 2.0-complaint driver. 
               the <productname>uPortal</productname> development team uses <ulink url="http://hsql.oron.ch/">
               HypersonicSQL</ulink> to facilitate development, but some campuses deploy a uPortal instance 
               with IBM DB2, Oracle 8i, MS SQL server and others. Any RDBMS with a JDBC 2.0 compliant driver 
               should work with some additional setup and configuration work. 
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>A copy of the Apache Jakarta project's <ulink
                url="http://xml.apache.org/xalan/">Xalan</ulink> XSLT processor. 
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
       
         Once you have these tools available on your machine, you can proceed with compiling and configuring a
         portal instance from the <orgname>JA-SIG</orgname> <productname>uPortal</productname> sources. Skip the
         next section and see <xref linkend="sources" />, below.
      </para>
                   
    </sect2>

  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="quickstart" >
    <title>Downloading and installing a <productname>uPortal</productname> <quote>Quick Start</quote>
    Release</title>
    
    <para>The <productname>uPortal</productname> <quote>Quick Start</quote> releases only require that you have
    a 1.2.2 or later Java Virtual Machine and a web browser installed on the computer system that you wish to run
    the portal on.  Assuming you already have those items installed, you can proceed with the following procedure 
    for downloading and installing the <quote>Quick Start</quote> release. The procedure assumes you're going to 
    install and operate the portal on a UNIX-like operating system, but because <productname>uPortal</productname>,
    as a Java-based framework, is platform-independant, you should be able to follow the instructions for a 
    windows-based system simply by substituting the windows equivalent paths and DOS shell commands in place of the
    described UNIX paths and <application>tcsh</application> commands.     
    </para>
    
    <procedure>  
       <step>
          <para>As of this writing, the most current <quote>Quick Start</quote> release is 
             <filename class="zipfile">LaJolla.zip</filename>, which was released in May 2001. You can 
              obtain the release from the <orgname>JA-SIG</orgname> website, located at 
             <ulink url="http://www.mis2.udel.edu/ja-sig/portal.html">http://www.ja-sig.org/</ulink>. 
             Download <filename class="zipfile">LaJolla.zip</filename> from that link to your local 
             filesystem. Once the download is complete, you should have 9.8 MB file. 
          </para> 
       </step>
       <step>
          <para>
            Unizip your copy of <filename class="zipfile">LaJolla.zip</filename> using the unzip utility: 
            <userinput>unzip LaJolla.zip</userinput> 
          </para>
       </step>
       <step>
          <para>
            Obtain a directory listing: <userinput>cd LaJolla; ls</userinput>
          </para>
       </step>
       <step>
          <para>
            Verify that you have the following files and subdirectories:
          </para>
          <para>
             <screen>
             Volume in drive C is SYSTEM         Serial number is 2350:717C
             Directory of  C:\

             10/17/97   9:04         &lt;DIR&gt;    bin
             10/16/97  14:11         &lt;DIR&gt;    DOS
             10/16/97  14:40         &lt;DIR&gt;    Program Files
             10/16/97  14:46         &lt;DIR&gt;    TEMP
             10/17/97   9:04         &lt;DIR&gt;    tmp
             10/16/97  14:37         &lt;DIR&gt;    WINNT
             10/16/97  14:25             119  AUTOEXEC.BAT
              2/13/94   6:21          54,619  COMMAND.COM
             10/16/97  14:25             115  CONFIG.SYS
             11/16/97  17:17      61,865,984  pagefile.sys
              2/13/94   6:21           9,349  WINA20.386
             </screen>
          </para>
       </step>
       <step>
          <para>
            Verify that your <envar>JAVA_HOME</envar> environment variable exists and is pointed
            at the correct directory:
          </para>
          <substeps>
             <step>
                <para>
                   <userinput>printenv JAVA_HOME</userinput>
                </para>
                <para>
                   <screen>
                      &gt; /usr/local/jdk1.2.2
                   </screen>
                </para>
             </step>
             <step>
                <para>
                   <userinput>which java</userinput>
                </para>
                <para>
                   <screen>
                      &gt; /usr/local/jdk1.2.2/bin/java
                   </screen>
                </para>
                <para>
                   If the location of the java interpreter reported by the shell is a subdirectory of
                   the same directory reported by the <userinput>printenv JAVA_HOME</userinput> command,
                   you can be reasonably sure that your <envar>JAVA_HOME</envar> environment variable is
                   set correctly.                 
                </para>
             </step>
          </substeps>          
       </step>
       <step>
          <para>
          Now you're ready to run ant to perform the installation: <userinput>ant install</userinput>
          </para>
          <para>
             <screen>
               To be continued...
             </screen>
          </para>
       </step>
       
    </procedure>    
    
    
  </sect1> 

  <sect1 id="sources">
    <title>Configuring and Compiling the <orgname>JA-SIG</orgname> 
       <productname>uPortal</productname> Sources
    </title>
    
    <para>The <productname>uPortal</productname> development team uses a CVS repository to maintain
    the various revisions to the source code. Access to this repository requires a username and 
    password, which you'll have to obtain by first registering with the 
    <ulink url="https://spackler.mis.udel.edu/ClearingHouse/index.jsp">JA-SIG Clearinghouse</ulink>.
    The login name and password you set here will be the login and password you will use for 
    accessing the <orgname>JA-SIG</orgname> CVS repository. 
    </para>
    
    <para>Once you register, use your CVS client to access the source code repository. 
    </para>
    
  </sect1>   
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Running Your Instance</title>
    
    <para>Placeholder
    </para>
    
  </sect1>    

  <sect1>
    <title>Next Steps</title>
    
    <para>Placeholder
    </para>
    
  </sect1>   

    
</article>
